Guide to the Harry Randall: Fifteenth International Brigade Films and Photographs ALBA.PHOTO.011
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Harry Randall: Fifteenth International Brigade Films and Photographs
August 1937-September 1938
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV. Photographic Unit
ALBA.PHOTO.011
6.5 Linear Feet (approximately 2,000 black and white negatives and prints)
Under the supervision of Harry W. Randall, Jr, the Photographic Unit of the 15th International Brigade was charged with documenting the activities of the Brigade during the Spanish Civil War. The collection consists of 3 reels and 1,832 images taken by the Unit from August 1937 to September 1938 and captures the daily life of the volunteers in combat, in the camps, and in the towns, villages, and across the rugged terrain where the Brigade trained and participated in the fighting. In addition, the collection documents political assemblies, congresses, celebrations and the everyday activities of the Spanish populace.
Sponsor Note
Funding for the digitization of film reels and negatives in this collection was provided by Rickard and Carol-Jeanette Jorgensen, in honor of Harry W. Randall, Jr., head of the 15th International Brigade Photo Unit, and Doreen Randall.
Custodial History
The Harry Randall: 15th International Brigade Photograph Collection represents a substantial portion of the work done by the Photo Unit during the Spanish Civil War. A large body of original negatives and prints was brought to New York from Spain by Harry Randall, who produced additional prints, some of which were distributed to surviving veterans or used in publications. The bulk of the material was left in the Veterans' office, and over the years some of the items were dispersed or lost. Randall and the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade donated the remaining material to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives in July 1999. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Harry W. Randall, Jr.
Harry W. Randall, Jr. was born in December 1915 in Spokane, Washington and raised in Portland, Oregon. He was the oldest of three children born to Harry W. Randall, Sr., an insurance adjuster, and Frances E. Randall, a schoolteacher. As a young man he developed an interest in motion pictures and, after graduating from Grant High School in 1934, enrolled in Reed College in Portland. While there he was drawn into a world of political action, joining with other progressive students on campus to support labor causes and to protest the rise of fascism in Europe. He collected food for striking maritime workers in 1934 and distributed leaflets at a lumber-workers strike in 1935. He left Reed after a year, found work as a projectionist for an advertising agency and, with a friend, began distributing foreign films in Washington State and Oregon.
When the Civil War erupted in Spain Randall enlisted in the International Brigades -- battalions of foreign volunteers that supported the Republican Army -- to fight against Franco's fascist forces. Randall sailed from New York on the S.S. Georgic on June 12, 1937, arriving in Spain on July 1, 1937. Following training with the MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion in Tarazona he was promoted to the rank of Sergeant and became the Chief Photographer of the Photographic Unit of the 15th International Brigade. He served in Spain until the withdrawal of the volunteer forces and returned to the United States on the S.S. Ausonia on December 20, 1938.
Randall relocated to Canada and found work with the National Film Board of Canada as the head of the Science Film unit. In 1944 he enlisted in the Canadian Army and served in England during the war making newsreels with the Film and Photo Unit. After the war, Randall resumed work with the National Film Board. He returned to New York City in 1952 and for the next 30 years produced, edited, and directed medical films. Randall married Doreen Cavalier, a registered nurse, in 1956 and the couple had two children and settled in Northern New Jersey. In 1983 Randall retired from the American Cancer Society after 18 years as the director of the organisation's film unit.
15th International Brigade Photographic Unit
The Photographic Unit of the 15th International Brigade was charged with creating a photographic record of the 15th Brigade for publication in the Brigade's newsletter Volunteer for Liberty, and for distribution to news outlets in the United States, England, and Canada. The photos were intended to boost the morale of the volunteers in Spain and foster sympathy and support for the Republican Army abroad. In addition to Randall, the unit was staffed by photographers Benjamin Katine and Anthony B. Drossel, as well as lab technician William H. Oderaka. The team was given full access to move about the camps, chronicling the troops at rest, and venturing to the front to capture scenes of the battalions in the trenches and under fire.
As part of their routine, each photographer logged and processed the film he shot. Every photograph was assigned a unique number, which was etched into the negative, and given a caption, which was recorded in one of five logs. Photographs were placed in albums, and copies were distributed to the press. Extra prints were sold to the troops for a nominal fee. Although initially successful in procuring the necessary photographic equipment to carry out their work, as the war progressed lack of film and printing paper hampered the unit's operation. Film development under battle conditions also proved challenging. Like the rest of the Brigade the development lab was a mobile unit, and was required to retreat or advance on short notice. On more than one occasion film and equipment were sacrificed or lost.
Following the war, Randall returned to the United States and brought with him the Brigade's photographic archives - negatives, albums of prints, and logs. In January of 1939 Randall spent several weeks in the New York Film and Photo League darkroom developing a complete set of fresh prints and making enlargements of all of the photographs taken by the unit in Spain. At the request of the British veterans, Randall also made 8x10 inch prints of images of the British Battalion and sent them along with copy negatives to the veterans' organization in England. In the intervening years the prints, negatives, and logs passed through many hands (most often fellow veterans). In the course of changing stewardship, many prints were dispersed, the original logs separated, and the albums disassembled. This collection represents the most complete record of the Photographic Unit's work in Spain.
When the Tamiment Library at New York University acquired the ALBA collections in 2001, the Randall collection was inventoried and reassembled. The images were assigned new control numbers (e.g. ALBA PHOTO 11-0001). Although the Photo Unit's handwritten logs have apparently vanished, the images have been matched whenever possible to their captions with the aid of extant typed transcriptions of the original lists. Where no captions were available, a brief description of the image appears in brackets.
Scope and Content Note
The Harry Randall: 15th International Brigade Photograph Collection spans the period from August 1937 to September 1938 and contains 1,832 black and white images taken by members of the Photo Unit of the 15th International Brigade during their tour of duty in Spain. The collection is comprised of 3 reels, 1,534 original negatives (ranging in size from 1.1 x 1.5 to 3 x 4.25 inches), and 626 prints (ranging in size from 1.5 x 1 to 8 x 10 inches). Some of the prints came directly from the albums created by the Photo Unit; original numbers and notations are in Randall's hand and the black paper from the photo album still adheres to the back of the prints. The collection also includes 348 copy negatives of which 203 were acquired by ALBA in the 1990s from the International Brigade Archives, housed in the Russian State Archive of Socio-Political History, Moscow. A number of the images are available in more than one format. Consult the collection inventory for details.
The collection documents the activities of the battalions that made up the 15th International Brigade including the American Lincoln and Washington Battalions (commonly known as the Abraham Lincoln Brigade); the British Battalion; the Canadian MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion; the Dimitroff Battalion (volunteers from Yugoslavia); and the 24th Spanish Battalion (volunteers from Cuba). The images capture the daily life of the volunteers in combat, in the camps, and in the towns, villages, and across the rugged terrain where the Brigade trained and participated in the fighting. In addition, the collection documents political assemblies, congresses, celebrations and the everyday activities of the Spanish populace. Also included are images of visiting dignitaries, journalists and observers including Earl Browder, American military attache Stephen Fuqua, Robert Minor, Ernest Hemingway, Langston Hughes, Meyer Levin and Joseph North.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into six series based on format, with the photographs series representing the five original subseries (A-E) established by the Photographic Unit.
Within each subseries, images are arranged in roughly chronological order.
Missing Title
Series A: Miscellaneous, August 1937 - May 1938
Series B: Individual Portraits, September 1937 September 1938
Series C: Group Portraits, September 1937 August 1938
Series D: Miscellaneous, September 1937 June 1938; August 1938
Series E: Miscellaneous, January 1938 September 1938
Series F. Films
NOTE: Use ALBA PHOTO # for ordering and physical retrieval of prints and negatives. Negatives in this collection from the International Brigades Archives: Selected Images are housed in ALBA PHOTO #177.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA PHOTO 177, International Brigades Archive: Selected Images
ALBA VF Harry W. Randall, Jr. Oral History (transcript)
ALBA FILMS 001 "With the Lincoln Brigade in Spain": Film Footage of the 15th International Brigade shot by Harry Randall, Jr. (VHS copy: For access see staff.)
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access copies for films are available by appointment for reading room viewing only. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Negatives (photographic); Teruel (Spain); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Hospitals.; Belchite (Spain) -- History -- Siege, 1937.; Ebro River, Battle of the, Spain, 1938.; Marca (Spain).; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Campaigns.; Gandesa (Spain); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Pictorial works.; Quinto (Spain); Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Aerial operations.; Mollerusa (Spain); Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x African Americans.; Fuentes de Ebro (Spain); Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Participation, Yugoslavian.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Participation, British.; Black-and-white photographs.; Almuchel (Spain); Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Portraits.; New York Film and Photo League; North, Joseph; Randall, Harry W., Jr., 1915-; Robinson, John; Levin, Meyer, 1905-1981; Merriman, Robert Hale; Minor, Robert, 1884-1952; Nemeroff, Murray; Brown, Archie, 1911-1990.; Tisa, John; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Rolfe, Edwin, 1909-1954; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Wolff, Milton.; Wellman, Saul; Browder, Earl, 1891-1973; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Watt, George, 1913-1994; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. British Battalion; Bessie, Alvah Cecil, 1904-1985; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Dimitrov Battalion; Drossel, Anthony B.; Straus, Mark, 1909-1993; Digges, William, d. 1938; Dallet, Joe, 1907-1937; Copic, Vladimir, 1891-1939; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967; Hemingway, Ernest, 1899-1961; Fuqua, Stephen; Klein, Jack; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion; Katine, Benjamin.; Katine, Ben; Juventud Socialista Unificada
- Series A: Miscellaneous, August 1937-May 1938
  Scope and Content Note
  Series IIA: Miscellaneous, August 1937 - May 1938. The 148 images in this series are among the earliest in the collection. Pictured here are scenes from the battles of Quinto and Belchite. Photographs of the aftermath of aerial bombardment offer evidence of damaged factories, homes and churches. Also documented are artillery units and battalions on the move, and troops under fire at Fuentes de Ebro, and soldiers dug into trenches at the Teruel front.
  - Photo Unit #: A001 American engineers repair road to Quinto which was cut off by Fascists, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1213)
  - Photo Unit #: A003 Fascist machine-gun fortification covering the road into Quinto, Sep 1937 (Item 11-1214)
  - Photo Unit #: A005 Tanks going into action, Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1215)
  - Photo Unit #: A006 Headless corpse, Fascist, Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1164)
  - Photo Unit #: A007 Stick bombs captured at Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1165)
  - Photo Unit #: A008 Tanks moving up road before actions, Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1166)
  - Photo Unit #: A009 Fascist field piece smashed at Belchite, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1216)
  - Photo Unit #: A010 Demolished church building, Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1217)
  - Photo Unit #: A011 Demolished church building, Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1218)
  - Photo Unit #: A017 Tanks going into action, Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1167)
  - Photo Unit #: A018 Fascist mauser rifles captured at Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1168)
  - Photo Unit #: A019 Fascist front lines, Purburell Hill, Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1169)
  - Photo Unit #: A020 Fascist front lines, Purburell Hill, Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1170)
  - Photo Unit #: A021 Fascist blockhouse or dugout (Purburell Hill), Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1171)
  - Photo Unit #: A022 Fortified hill (Purburell) from which 15th International Brigade took 800 prisoners and a White Guard officer. Peter Daly killed here, Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1219)
  - Photo Unit #: A024 Purburell Hill (fortified Fascist positions), view from Republican lines looking along Zaragoza Road towards [?], Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1172)
  - Photo Unit #: A025 Purburell Hill (fortified Fascist positions), view from Republican lines looking along Zaragoza Road towards [?], Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1173)
  - Photo Unit #: A026 Internationals and Republican tank after action, Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1220)
  - Photo Unit #: A027 Purburell Hill, Fascist fortifications, Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1221)
  - Photo Unit #: A028 Fascist fortification and machine-gun nest, Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1222)
  - Photo Unit #: A030 Purburell Hill (Fascist fortifications), Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1174)
  - Photo Unit #: A031 Purburell Hill (Fascist fortifications), Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1175)
  - Photo Unit #: A032 Fascist officers refugio, Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1176)
  - Photo Unit #: A034 Purburell, Fascist officers quarters, Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1177)
  - Photo Unit #: A035 Puburell fortifications (Fascist), Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1178)
  - Photo Unit #: A037 Purburell, Fascist officer corpse and captured mortars, Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1179)
  - Photo Unit #: A038 Lincoln-Washington Battalion Machine-Gunner Company resting after Pina, Sep 1937 (Item 11-1180)
  - Photo Unit #: A040 After Lincoln-Washington Battalion mopped up barricade. Calle looking toward Calle Mayor towards Plaza San Agustin to Lincoln Church, Belchite, Sep 1937 (Item 11-1223)
  - Photo Unit #: A041 Fascist comandancia (Old Plaza de la Republica), Belchite, Sep 1937 (Item 11-0579)
  - Photo Unit #: A048 Observation post and captured Fascist fortification, Belchite, Sep 1937 (Item 11-0580)
  - Photo Unit #: A049 Factory on outskirts of Belchite occupied first by Dimitroff then used by Lincoln-Washington Battalion as jumping off position to attack Church of San Agustín, Belchite, Sep 1937 (Item 11-0581)
  - Photo Unit #: A050 Calle Joachim Coasta looking south from Plaza de la Republica (Plaza de Franco) road to Azoila, Belchite, Sep 1937 (Item 11-1224)
  - Photo Unit #: A051 House wrecked by Republican artillery and Fascist airplanes, Sep 1937 (Item 11-1225)
  - Photo Unit #: A054 View looking down Calle Mayor from Goya Gate toward Fascist comandancia militar and Plaza de la Republica, Belchite, Sep 1937 (Item 11-1226)
  - Photo Unit #: A055 Falangist barracks, Belchite, Sep 1937 (Item 11-1227)
  - Photo Unit #: A060 Republican batteries outside Belchite, Sep 1937 (Item 11-1228)
  - Photo Unit #: A062 15th Brigade anti-tank gun position on hill behind town firing into back of Fascist Commandancia Militar [Military Command], Belchite, Sep 1937 (Item 11-1181)
  - Photo Unit #: A063 Tank moving down Zaragoza-Belchite Road toward town. Sign on Left. Road to Codo. On right LV road to town, Belchite, Sep 1937 (Item 11-1182)
  - Photo Unit #: A064 Approach road to Belchite, to church and Fabrica. Taken in direction of Lincoln-Washington attack from Battalion's first position, Belchite, Sep 1937 (Item 11-1229)
  - Photo Unit #: A065 American Artillery unit at front, Aragon offensive (Belchite), Sep 1937 (Item 11-1230)
  - Photo Unit #: A066 Fascist prisoners being taken to Division near Brigade Estado Mayor [Headquarters], 3 km outside Belchite on the Zaragoza Road, Belchite, Sep 1937 (Item 11-1183)
  - Photo Unit #: A068 Republic artillery before Belchite, Sep 1937 (Item 11-1184)
  - Photo Unit #: A069 A battery, Belchite, Sep 1937 (Item 11-1231)
  - Photo Unit #: A070 British anti-tank battery in action at Fuentes de Ebro, Oct 1937 (Item 11-1232)
  - Photo Unit #: A072 Thane Summers of MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion on manuevers, Tarazona Front, Aug 1938 (Item 11-1830)
  - Photo Unit #: A073 Saul Wellman, Robert Thomson, David Doran, Fuentes de Ebro, Oct 1937 (Item 11-0582)
  - Photo Unit #: A074 African-American Machine-Gunner in Lincoln-Washington trenches, Fuentes de Ebro, Oct 1937 (Item 11-0583)
  - Photo Unit #: A077 Fortified "Stations of the Cross," Codo, Sep 1937 (Item 11-1185)
  - Photo Unit #: A079 Fortified "Stations of the Cross," Codo, Sep 1937 (Item 11-1186)
  - Photo Unit #: A082 Fortified "Stations of the Cross," Codo, Sep 1937 (Item 11-1187)
  - Photo Unit #: A083 Fortified "Stations of the Cross," Codo, Sep 1937 (Item 11-1188)
  - Photo Unit #: A085 Moving anti-tank gun into firing position, Ambite, Nov 1937 (Item 11-1233)
  - Photo Unit #: A088 Staff during action at Fuentes de Ebro, Oct 1937 (Item 11-1193)
  - Photo Unit #: A089 At front, Fuentes de Ebro, Oct 1937 (Item 11-0584)
  - Photo Unit #: A092 Fascist air bombardment, Fuentes de Ebro, Oct 1937 (Item 11-0585)
  - Photo Unit #: A095 With English Battalion in trenches at Fuentes de Ebro, Oct 1937 (Item 11-1799)
    General note
    Available Formats: Copy Negative; Moscow negative
    (Moscow Number: 5/184/10)
  - Photo Unit #: A096 English Battalion in trenches at Fuentes de Ebro, [six soldiers], Oct 1937 (Item 11-1792)
    Available Formats:
    (Moscow Number: 5/184/2)
  - Photo Unit #: A097 Observers Jack Freeman and Peter Ambrosiac [?], Lincoln-Washington, Fuentes de Ebro, Oct 1937 (Item 11-0586)
  - Photo Unit #: A098 Lincoln-Washington Battalion observers in trenches, Fuentes de Ebro, Oct 1937 (Item 11-1821)
    (Moscow Number: 5/185/38)
  - Photo Unit #: A099 In Lincoln-Washington trenches, Fuentes de Ebro, Oct 1937 (Item 11-0587)
  - Photo Unit #: A100 In Lincoln-Washington trenches, Fuentes de Ebro, Oct 1937 (Item 11-0588)
    Available Formats: Original Negative; Moscow negative
    (Moscow Number: 5/185/39)
  - Photo Unit #: A105 Roy (Red) Mouton, MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion observer, Fuentes de Ebro, Oct 1937 (Item 11-1842)
  - Photo Unit #: A107 Estado Mayor [Headquarters] at front, Fuentes de Ebro [with tents and car], Oct 1937 (Item 11-1234)
  - Photo Unit #: A108 Replacements arriving at Quinto being addressed by David Doran [not visible], Oct 1937 (Item 11-1235)
    Available Formats: Print; Moscow negative
    (Moscow Number: 5/189/24)
  - Photo Unit #: A110 David Doran addressing troops at Fuentes de Ebro, Oct 1937 (Item 11-1779)
    (Moscow Number: 5/181/8)
  - Photo Unit #: A111 David Doran addressing troops, replacements for Brigade at Quinto during action at Fuentes de Ebro, Oct 1937 (Item 11-1778)
    (Moscow Number: 5/181/4)
  - Photo Unit #: A114 Airplane bombardment, Fuentes de Ebro, Oct 1937 (Item 11-1236)
  - Photo Unit #: A115 Airplane bombardment, Fuentes de Ebro, Oct 1937 (Item 11-1237)
  - Photo Unit #: A117 Fascist corpse, Quinto, Aug 1937 (Item 11-1238)
  - Photo Unit #: A120 Spanish machine-gun nest of British Battalion on maneuvers, Mondejar, [four soldiers], undated (Item 11-1798)
    (Moscow Number: 5/184/9)
  - Photo Unit #: A124 Three companies marching in from maneuvers, British Battalion, Mondejar [copy negative; transferred from the Victor Berch Papers, ALBA 080], Dec 1937 (Item 11-1880)
  - Photo Unit #: A139 Engineers at work, Argente [copy negative; transferred from the Victor Berch Papers, ALBA 080], Jan 1938 (Item 11-1881)
  - Photo Unit #: A142 Engineers at work, Argente [in a trench], Jan 1938 (Item 11-1239)
  - Photo Unit #: A143 Three soldiers on lookout [one African-American], Feb 1938 (Item 11-1240)
  - Photo Unit #: A144 15th International Brigade, Spaniards at Teruel sector, Jan 1938 (Item 11-1241)
  - Photo Unit #: A149 MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion sappers or observers [?], Argente, Jan 1938 (Item 11-1242)
    Available Formats: Copy NegativePrint
  - Photo Unit #: A160 English Battalion marching to the front, Fuerte Caliente, Jan 1938 (Item 11-1243)
  - Photo Unit #: A161 Engineer Battalion food truck, Rillo [with men gathered around it], Jan 1938 (Item 11-1244)
  - Photo Unit #: A164 British Battalion, machine-gun nest, Rillo, Jan 1938 (Item 11-1245)
  - Photo Unit #: A174 Camp Kitchen [2 men with pots] (Item 11-1855)
  - Photo Unit #: A176 Observers at front near Teruel, Jan 1938 (Item 11-1246)
  - Photo Unit #: A179 [soldiers in trench with rifles] (Item 11-1856)
  - Photo Unit #: A184 A tank and Abe Lewis near Teruel [copy negative; transferred from the Victor Berch Papers, ALBA 080], Jan 1938 (Item 11-1882)
  - Photo Unit #: A197 Lieutenant [William] Digges and Dave Doran and armored car, Teruel [copy negative; transferred from the Victor Berch Papers, ALBA 080], Jan 1938 (Item 11-1883)
  - Photo Unit #: A200 [view of the city with damage], Teruel, Jan 1938 (Item 11-1247)
  - Photo Unit #: A203 Bridge, Teruel, Jan 1938 (Item 11-1248)
  - Photo Unit #: A204 Damaged building, Teruel, Jan 1938 (Item 11-0873)
  - Photo Unit #: A212 MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion Machine-Gunner Company headquarters [in cave]; Makela, Teruel, Jan 1938 (Item 11-1249)
  - Photo Unit #: A214 MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion, Teruel [3 men with cooking pot], Jan 1938 (Item 11-1250)
  - Photo Unit #: A215 MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion, Teruel, Jan 1938 (Item 11-0874)
  - Photo Unit #: A217 MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion, Teruel, Jan 1938 (Item 11-1251)
  - Photo Unit #: A218 Pablo Carbonell, killed in action, MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion, Teruel, Jan 1938 (Item 11-0875)